Narrator: Is too much choice making us unhappy?
Speaker: Buying jeans isn’t as easy as it used to be.
Years ago, there was only one kind of jeans – probably Levis.
Nowadays, there are hundreds – different styles, different colours, different lengths, with buttons, with zips.
There are so many options that you feel the perfect pair must be waiting for you somewhere…
And it isn’t just jeans. In big supermarkets we have to choose between thousands of products –
my local supermarket has 35 different kinds of milk!
When we’re buying clothes or electrical gadgets, ordering a coffee in a café,
looking for a hotel on a travel website, deciding which TV channel to watch,
or even choosing a future partner on a dating website,
we constantly have to choose from hundreds of possibilities.
People often think that being able to choose from a lot of options is a good thing.
However, university researchers have discovered that too much choice is making us feel unhappy and dissatisfied.
The problem is that we have so many options that we get stressed every time we have to make a decision
because we’re worried about making the wrong one.
Then when we choose one thing, we feel bad because we think we are missing other opportunities,
and this makes us dissatisfied with what we’ve chosen.
Research also shows that we feel happier when we have less choice.
In a study, Professor Mark Lepper at Stanford University
found that people who tried six kinds of jam  and then chose one
felt happier with their choice than those who were offered 24 jams to taste.
But if all this choice is bad for us, what can we do about it?
Professor Lepper suggests that we should try to relax when we have to decide what to buy.
‘Don’t take these choices too seriously or it will become stressful,’ he says.
‘If you pick a sofa from IKEA in 30 seconds,
you’ll feel better than if you spend hours researching sofas – because you won’t know what you’re missing.’